<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An acte for certayne ordinaunces in the Kynges Maiesties dominion and principalitie of VVales</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1543</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9409.9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22939216</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22939216</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25950</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22946)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25950)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1792:48)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An acte for certayne ordinaunces in the Kynges Maiesties dominion and principalitie of VVales</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[27] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Thomas Barthelet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1543]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of title: Anno XXXIIII. et XXXV. Henrici VIII.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Publisher from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶ B⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wales --  Politics and government.</term>
               <term>Wales --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayne Henley</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayne Henley</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25950:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25950:1"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> AN ACTE FOR CERTAYNE OR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunces in the kynges maieſties dominion and principalitie of VVales.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr ſoueraigne lorde the kynges maieſtie of his tender zele and affection, that he bereth towardes his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge and obedient ſubiectes of his dominion principalitie and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey of Wales, for good rule and order to be from henſforth kepte and maynteyned within the ſame, wherby his ſayd ſubiectes may growe and ryſe to more welth and proſperitie, hath deuyſed and made dyuerſe ſundry good and neceſſarye ordinaunces, which his maieſtie, of his moſt abundant goodnes, at the humble ſuite and peticion of his ſaid ſubiectes of Wales, is pleaſed and contented, to be enacted, by thaſſent of the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, and by the aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the ſame, in maner and fourme, as here after enſueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>FYRST THAT</hi> his gracis ſayde domynyon princypalite and countrey of Wales, be from henſforth deuided into .xii. ſhires, of the which .viii. haue ben ſhires of longe and auncient tyme, that is to ſaye: the ſhires of Glamorgan, Carmarthin, Pembroke, Cardigan, Flynt, Caernaruan, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleſey, &amp; Merionneth, And foure of the ſaid twelue ſhires be newlye made and ordeyned to be ſhires, by an acte made at the parliament, holden at Weſtmynſter, in the .xvij. yere of our ſayd ſoueraigne lordes mooſt noble reigne: that is to ſay, the ſhires of Radnor, Breknok, Mountgomery, and Denbigh, ouer and beſides, the ſhire of Mommoth, and diuers other do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, lordſhippes and manors, in the marches of Wales, vnited and annexed to the ſhires of Salop<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Herforde, and Glouceſtre, as by the ſayd late acte more plainly appereth.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the lymytations of the hundredes, of late made within the ſaid ſhires, by vertue of his graces commiſſion, directed out of his highe courte of Chancery, and agayne returned into the ſame, ſhall ſtande in full ſtrength, force and effecte, accordinge to the ſayd limitation: Except ſuch of the ſame, as ſyth that tyme haue ben altered or chaunged, by vertue of any acte, or actes of parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t al redy made, or that ſhalbe altered or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, by any acte, or actes, in this preſent ſeſſion to be made.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that there ſhalbe and remayne a Preſident and counſaile in the ſaid dominion and principalite of Wales, and the marches of the ſame, with all officers, clerkes, and incidentes to the ſame, in maner and forme as hath ben hertofore vſed and accuſtomed. Whiche preſydent and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile ſhall haue power and auctoritie, to here and determine by their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and diſcretions, ſuch cauſes and matters as be, or hereafter ſhall be aſſigned to them by the kinges maieſtie, as hertofore hath ben accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and vſed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25950:2"/>
            <p>¶ Item that there ſhalbe holden and kept, Seſſions twyſe in euery yere, in euery of the ſayde ſhires, in the ſayde domynyon and principalitye of Wales: That is to ſaye, in the ſhires of Glamorgan, Breknok, Radnor, Caermerthin, Pembroke, Cardigan, Mountgomerey, Denbigh, Flynt, Caernaruan, Merionneth, &amp; Angleſey, the which Seſſions ſhalbe called the kynges great Seſſions in Wales.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the iuſtice of Cheſtre, for the tyme beynge, ſhall holde and kepe Seſſions twyſe in euery yere, in the ſhires of Denbygh, Flynt, and Mountgomery, and haue nothynge but his olde fee of an hundred poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des yerely for the ſame.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the iuſtice of Northwales ſhall in lykewiſe holde, and kepe Seſſions twyſe euery yere, in euery of the ſayde ſhires of Caernaruan, Merionneth, and Angleſey, and ſhall haue yerely of the kynges maieſtie a yerely fee of fyfty poundes for the ſame.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that one perſon, lerned in the lawes of this realme of Englande, by the kynges maieſtie to be named and appoynted, ſhalbe Iuſtice of the ſhires of Radnor, Breknok, and Glamorgan, and ſhall in lykewyſe holde, and kepe Seſſions twiſe in euery yere, in euerye of the ſame ſhires, and ſhall haue yerely of the kynges maieſtie fyfty poundes for his fee.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that one other perſon, lerned in the lawes of this realme, to be appoynted, as is aforeſayde, ſhalbe Iuſtice of the ſhires of Caermerthin, Pembroke, and Cardigan, and ſhall in lykewiſe holde and kepe Seſſions twiſe in euery yere, in euery of the ſame ſhires: and ſhall alſo haue yerely of the kynges maieſtie fyftie poundes for his fee.</p>
            <p>¶ Item the ſaide perſonnes or Iuſtices, and euery of them now beynge, or that herafter ſhalbe, ſhall haue ſeuerall letters patentes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions for their offices, vnder the kynges great ſeale of Englande, to be exerciſed by them ſelues, or their ſufficient deputies, according to the purpoſes and intentes, in their ordinaunces ſpecified.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, that their commyſſions, to them alredye graunted, vnder the ſaid great ſeale, ſhall ſtande in force and effect, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the tenour of the ſame: onleſſe it ſhall pleaſe the kynges maieſtie herafter, to alter or chaunge them, or any of them, this preſent article laſt before expreſſed in any wyſe not withſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that euery of the ſayd Iuſtices, within the lymittes of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions and auctorities, to them appointed as is afore ſaid, ſhall holde all maner of plees of the Crowne, at and in the ſayd Seſſions, in as large and ample maner, as the kynges chief Iuſtice of England, and other the kynges Iuſtices of the kynges bench there, or any of them, may do in their places or elles where within the realme of Englande. And alſo to holde plees of aſſiſes, and all other plees and actions reall perſonall and mixte, in as large and ample maner, as the kynges chiefe Iuſtice of the common place in Englande, and other Iuſtices of the ſame place, or any of them, may do in the realme of Englande.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25950:2"/>
            <p>¶ Item that euery of the ſaid Iuſtices of Wales, ſhall haue power and auctoritie, to enquire of all treaſons, murthers, felonies, riottes, routes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laufull aſſembles, extorcions, embraceries, maynteynaunces, reteynors, concelementes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> contemptes, and all other offences and euyl dedes, of what natures, names, or qualities ſo euer they be, done, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, or perpetrated, within the limittes of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions &amp; auctorities, againſt the fourme of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon law of the realm of England, or of any ſtatutes of the ſame, and to here &amp; determine the premiſſes, and euery of them: and generally to miniſter common iuſtice to all and ſinguler the kinges ſubiectes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the limittes of their commiſſions and auctorities, accordinge to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes ſtatutes and cuſtomes of the realme of Englande, and according to this preſent ordinaunce.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that euery of the ſaid ſeſſions ſhalbe kepte and contynued by the ſpace of .vi. daies, in euery of the ſaide ſhires, at either of the ſaide tymes as is and hath ben vſed within the ſaide thre ſhires of North wales. And that the ſaide Iuſtices ſhall cauſe open proclamations to be made in the ſhire tounes, what time &amp; place they purpoſe to kepe their ſaid ſeſſions .xv. daies at the leaſt, before they kepe the ſame: to thintent the kynges ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes may haue knowlege therof.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that daies ſhalbe giuen in all plees plaintes proceſſe and adiour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentes from day to day, and ſeſſions to ſeſſions, by the diſcretion of the ſaid Iuſtices, within the limittes of their auctorities, for the good and ſpedy miniſtracion of Iuſtice, to all and ſinguler the kinges ſubiectes, as is or hath ben vſed in Northwales.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that one originall ſeale, deuiſed by the kinges highnes for iuſtice to be miniſtred in the ſaide thre ſhires of Northwales, That is to ſay, the ſhires of Merionneth, Caernaruan, and Angleſey, ſhalbe and remayne in the charge keping and cuſtodie of the chamberleyne of Northwales. And that one other originall ſeale, deuiſed by the kinges maieſtie, for miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of iuſtice to be vſed in the ſaid ſhires of Carmerthin, Pembroke, and Cardigan, ſhalbe and remayne in the charge and keping of the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyne of Southwales. And that likewiſe one other originall ſeale, deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the kynges maieſtie, for mynyſtracion of iuſtice to be vſed in the ſaid thre ſhires of Breknok, Radnor, and Glamorgan, ſhalbe and remaine in the charge and cuſtody of the ſtewarde and chamberleyn of Breknok. And that alſo one other originall ſeale, deuiſed by the kinges maieſtie, for miniſtration of iuſtice, to be miniſtred within the ſaid ſhires of Denbigh and Mountgomerie, ſhalbe and remayne in the charge keping and cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of the Steward and Chamberlein of Denbigh. And that the originall ſeale of Cheſter, ſhall be and ſtande for the originall ſeale of Flint, for iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to be miniſtred in the ſaid ſhire of Flint: and ſhalbe and remayne in the charge keping and cuſtodie of the Chamberleine of Cheſter.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the ſaid Stewardes and Chamberleyns ſhall ſeale with the ſaid ſeales: that is to ſay, euery one of them ſhall ſeale with the ſeale, to
<pb facs="tcp:25950:3"/>his charge committed, all maner of originall writtes and proces, returna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before the ſaid Iuſtices, at the ſeſſions to be holden in euery of the ſaid ſhires, in maner and forme as is aforeſaide: and ſhall ſeuerally accompte and anſwere the kinges maieſtie, for the profittes of the ſame ſeale. And that none of the ſaid ſtewardes, chamberleynes, or chauncellours, hauinge the charge and kepinge of the ſaid ſeales, ſhall by occaſion therof, or by colour of any of their offices, compell or cauſe any perſon or perſons, inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited within any of the ſaid .xii. ſhires, to appere before them ſelfes or their deputies: ne ſhal haue power or auctoritie, to here or determyne any plees of the crowne, nor other cauſes or matters of iuſtice otherwiſe then in this ordinaunce is limitted and expreſſed: But ſhall haue the charge and ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the ſaide ſeales, to ſeale all ſuch originall writtes &amp; proces, as ſhal be returnable before the ſaid iuſtices, in their ſaide ſeſſions, as is before ſpecified, and as here after ſhal be declared, which writtes and proces ſhal be vſed made ſealed and returned, in maner and forme, as hath ben vſed before the Iuſtice in North wales.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all ſuche perſons, as now be, or here after ſhall be the kinges highnes ſtewardes, chamberleines, or chauncellours, within any of the ſaid .xii. ſhires, which by reaſon of their ſayd offices, haue charges for the recept collection or accompte, of and for the kinges rentes, reuenues, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes or profittes, to be due to his maieſtie, within the ſayde dominion of Wales, may directe proces, vnder the ſaide ſeale, beynge in their charge and cuſtodie, within the limittes of their auctorities onely agaynſt bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffes, reues, fermours, and other miniſters accomptant, to appere before them ſelfes, to anſwere to and for any the kynges reuenues fermes rentes or profittes, and for none other cauſes, nor againſt any other perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in lyke maner and fourme as they haue ben accuſtomed in that caſe to do.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all ſtewardes of any lordſhips or manors in Wales, ſhall and may kepe and hold ſuch leetes, lawdayes, and courtbarons, as apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth &amp; belongeth to the lordeſhips and manors, wherof they be ſtewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and to holde plees by playnte, vnder the ſumme of <abbr>.xlſ.</abbr> in euery ſuche courtbaron: and haue and enioye all other auctorities, commodities and profittes, as ſtewardes of leetes, lawdayes and court barons in England commonly haue, and ben vſed to haue, by reaſon of the ſaide offices, and none other: any law vſage or cuſtome, in the ſaide dominion of Wales, hertofore had to the contrary herof not withſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶ Item prouided alwayes and be it enacted, that the ſaide ſtewardes, nor any of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor the ſhirefe of the ſaid counties in Wales, ſhall haue any power or auctoritie, to enquire of any maner of felonye, in any ſuche leete, lawdaye, or tourne, within the ſaide dominion to be holden.</p>
            <p>And that from henſforth no leete nor lawday be kepte by the Steward or other officer, of any lordſhippe or manor in the ſaid dominion of Wales: but in ſuch lordſhippes and places, where it was accuſtomed to be kepte,
<pb facs="tcp:25950:3"/>before the makynge of the acte of parliament, concernyng Wales, made in the .xxvi. yere of our ſayde ſoueraygne lordes reigne. So alwayes the place, where ſuch court ſhalbe kept, be mete &amp; conuenient for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all Maires, Bailiffes and heed officers of corporate townes in Wales, maye holde plees, and determyne actions, and do euery other thinge, concerninge common iuſtice, according to their lawfull grauntes and laudable cuſtomes of ſuch townes: ſo alwayes they folow the courſe trade and faſcion, of the lawes and cuſtomes of the realme of Englande, and not of any walſhe lawes or cuſtomes. And that in euery of the ſayde townes they may trie all iſſues ioyned, or herafter to be ioyned, in any acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on perſonall, by .vi. men, accordynge as hertofore in dyuerſe places of the ſayd countrey it hath ben vſed: Any thynge conteyned in this acte to the contrary not withſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, and be it enacted by the auctoritie aforeſaid, that for as moch as there be diuers &amp; many ſmall boroughes and townes corporate within the ſayd dominion of Wales: wherof many haue theyr commenceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by grauntes, made from the lordes marchers, and ſome by other meanes: our ſayde ſoueraine lorde ſhall from henſforth, by vertue of this acte, haue full power and auctorytie, by his letters patentes, to be inrolled in his graces highe courte of Chancery, at any tyme within ſeuen yeres, hereafter nexte enſuynge to thend of this preſent parliament, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, adnihilate, and diſſolue ſuche and as many of the ſayde boroughes and townes corporate, and all liberties &amp; cuſtomes of the ſame, as to his highnes ſhalbe thought expedient, to thintent his maieſtie, at his graces pleaſure, may newly erect, ordeyne and make, ſuch and as many other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes and townes corporate within the ſayde domynyon, beinge more apte and conuenient for that purpoſe, and endue them with ſuch liberties and francheſes, as to his moſt excellent wiſedome ſhalbe thought neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, for the welth of the ſaid countrey.</p>
            <p>¶ Item the kynges maieſtie is pleaſed and contented, of his moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious goodnes, that ſuch as haue patentes of any office of Stewardſhips, chamberleynſhyppes, chauncellourſhippes, or Iuſticeſhippes, within the ſayd domynyon of Wales, for terme of their lyues, ſhall haue and enioye their certayne ordinarie and annuell fees of money, vſed and accuſtomed to be payed and borne by the kynges highnes, by vertue of any theyr let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patentes, during their intereſt therin: but in no wiſe to take or claime any caſuall fees, claymed by coloure of their offices, contrarie to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ordinaunce: Any cuſtome in Wales, or any thynge in this acte to the contrary not withſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Item ouer and beſides the ſaid originall ſeales, there ſhalbe four iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ſeales, deuiſed by the kinges maieſtie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherof one ſhall remayne with the Iuſtice of Cheſter, which is appoynted by this act, to be Iuſtice of the ſhires of Flynt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Denbigh, and Mountgomerye, to be vſed within the ſaid ſhires to ſeale all iudiciall proces and bylles, that ſhall be ſued before the
<pb facs="tcp:25950:4"/>ſaid iuſtice, in the ſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be holden within the ſame ſhires. And that one other of the ſaid iudiciall ſeales, ſhall likewiſe remayne, &amp; be in the charge &amp; cuſtodie of the ſaid Iuſtice of Northwales. And that the third of the ſaid ſeales, ſhalbe and remayne in the cuſtodie and charge, of the Iuſtice of the thre ſhires of Glamorgan, Breknok, &amp; Radnor. And the fourth of the ſaid ſeales ſhall remayne in the charge and cuſtodie of the Iuſtice of the ſayde thre ſhires, of Pembroke, Carmerthin, and Cardigan. And the ſayd Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhall ſeale with the ſayd iudiciall ſeales: that is to ſay, euery of them with the ſeale committed to his charge and cuſtodie, as well all bylles, as all other iudiciall proces, that ſhall be ſued before them in the ſayde ſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vppon any oryginall bylles or wryttes: and all other proceſſe, that ſhalbe awarded from any of the ſaid Iuſtices, ſhalbe ſealed with the ſayd iudiciall ſeale.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that euery of the ſayd Iuſtices ſhall accompte and anſwere to the kynges maieſtie for the profittes of the ſaid ſeale, beyng in his charge and cuſtodie, in maner and forme as herafter ſhalbe declared.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the Teſte of euery byll and iudiciall proces, that ſhall paſſe vnder the ſayd iudiciall ſeale, ſhalbe vnder the name of ſuche of the ſayde Iuſtices, from whom ſuch bill or iudiciall proceſſe ſhall paſſe, in lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and forme as is vſed in the common place in Englande.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all actions real and myxt, atteintes, conſpiracies, aſſiſes, and quare impedit, appeles of murther and felonye, and all actions grounded vpon any ſtatutes, ſhall be ſued by originall wryttes, to be opteyned &amp; ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the ſaid original ſeale, returnable before the ſaid Iuſtices at their ſeſſions, within the lymittes of their auctorities, in maner and forme as is afore mencioned.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all maner of perſonall actions, as dette, detynue, treſpas, accompte, and ſuch lyke, amounting to the ſumme of fourty ſhillinges, or aboue ſhalbe ſued by wryttes originall, to be opteyned and ſealed as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd, or by billes, at the pleaſure of the partye ſuinge the ſame, before the ſayd Iuſtices, within the lymittes of their auctorities, as is vſed in Northwales. And that all perſonall actions, vnder the ſomme of fourtie ſhillinges, that is to ſay, dette, treſpas, detinue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> accompte, and ſuch lyke, ſhall and may be ſued, before any of the ſayd Iuſtices, in the ſaid ſeſſions, by bill as it is vſed in Northwales. And that euery originall byll, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge actions perſonalles, ſhall be ſealed with the kynges iudiciall ſeale, being in the cuſtodie of the ſaid Iuſtice, before whom ſuch perſonall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by bille ſhalbe brought, and commenced. And that ſuche fees ſhalbe paied for the writinge and ſealyng of ſuch originall writtes and bylles, as herafter ſhalbe expreſſed: That is to ſay, for the ſealyng of euery original writte to be ſued in, and vppon the cauſes aforeſayde: and for euery byll, to be purſued in actions perſonall, wherof the dette, and damage amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to the ſumme of fourtye ſhillinges, or aboue, the partyes purſuinge the ſame, ſhall paye for the ſeale of euery ſuche wrytte or bylle, ſex pens.
<pb facs="tcp:25950:4"/>And for euery iudiciall proces, to be ſued vpon any ſuch originall writte, or bille, the parries purſuinge ſuch iudiciall proces, ſhall pay for the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge therof, ſeuen pens: wherof the kinges maieſtie ſhall haue ſex pens, and the Iuſtice, ſealinge ſuche iudiciall proceſſe, ſhall haue one peny.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that euery bill in perſonal action, wherof the det, duitie or damage amounteth not to fourty ſhillinges: and all maner iudicial proceſſe to be ſued vpon the ſame, ſhall alſo be ſealed with the kynges ſayde iudiciall ſeale: and the parties purſuynge the ſame, ſhall pay for the ſeale of euery ſuch byll, and iudiciall proces, theruppon to be ſued, thre pens, wherof the kynges maieſtie to haue two pens and the Iuſtice, ſealinge ſuche proceſſe, to haue a peny.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all writtes of Scire <abbr>fac,</abbr> and writtes of good aberinge, or for the peax, or writtes of Superſede as vppon the ſame, and all other proceſſe to be ſued from the ſayde Iuſtices, vpon any recorde or ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, admitted by any of the ſayde Iuſtices, within the limittes of their auctorities, ſhall alſo be ſealed with the ſayde iudiciall ſeale. And that the parties, purſuinge for the ſame, ſhall paye for the ſeale, of euery ſuche writte and proceſſe, ſeuen pens: wherof the kynges highneſſe ſhall haue ſex pens, and the Iuſtice, by whome ſuche proceſſe ſhall be ſealed, a peny. And that euery exemplyfication, vpon any recorde, before any of the ſaid Iuſtices, ſhall be ſealed with the kinges ſaide iudiciall ſeale: and the parties purſuinge the ſame, ſhall paye for the ſeale therof, twenty pens wherof the kinges highnes ſhall haue ſextene pens, and the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſealynge the ſame, four pens.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that recoueries and fynes, concordes and Warrantes of attour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for the ſame, ſhall and maye be taken before euerye of the ſaide Iuſtices, of landes, tenementes, and hereditamentes, within his aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, by force of his generall commiſſion, without any writte of <hi>Dedimus poteſtatem,</hi> to be ſued for the ſame, in like maner and fourme as is vſed to be taken, before the kynges chiefe Iuſtice, of his common place in Englande.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all fynes, herafter to be leuied before any of the ſaide Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with proclamation made the ſame ſeſſions, that the ſaide fine ſhal be engroſſed, and in two other great ſeſſions then nexte to be holden within the ſame countrey, ſhalbe of the ſame force and ſtrength to al purpoſes, as fynes leuied with proclamations be of, that be leuied before the Iuſtices of the common place in Englande.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that euery perſonne, ſuinge Writtes of Entree in the Poſte, or Wryttes of couenaunt, or any other Writtes, for any recouerye to be hadde, by aſſent of partyes, or otherwyſe, or for any fyne to be leuied, ſhall paye ſuche fynes to the kynges vſe, for the ſame, aſwell fynes Pro licentia concordandi, as all other maner of fynes, as is vſed in the kynges Chauncery, or elles where in any of the kinges Courtes of
<pb facs="tcp:25950:5"/>Englande: whiche fines ſhall be paied to ſuche perſons, as ſhall ſeale the originall writtes for that purpoſe: And that they ſhall accompte for the ſame in like fourme, as they ſhall do for the profittes of the ſaid originall ſeale, as is aforeſaide.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the kinges ſiluer, vpon euery fine to be leuied, ſhal be payed, as is vſed in the common place in Englande: that is to ſaye, two ſhillin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: which kinges ſiluer ſhall be payde to the Iuſtice, afore whom ſuche fyne ſhalbe leuied. Wherof the kinges highnes ſhall haue twenty pens: and the Prenotarie, entring the ſame, ſhall haue two pens: &amp; the Iuſtice, afore whome ſuche fine ſhall be leuied, other two pens. And that the ſame Iuſtice ſhall accompte for the kinges part therof, like as he ſhall for the profittes of the kinges iudiciall ſeale, committed to his charge, in maner and forme as is aforeſaide.</p>
            <p>¶ Item there ſhalbe foure Prenotaries for the makinge of all iudiciall proces, and for the enteringe of all plees proces and maters of recorde, in the ſeſſions to be holden before the ſaid Iuſtices: wherof one of the ſaide Prenotaries ſhall attende vpon the ſaide Iuſtice appoynted for the thre ſhires of Northwales: And one other ſhal attende vpon the Iuſtice, aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the thre ſhires of Flint, Denbigh, and Mountgomerie: And the thirde ſhall attende vppon the Iuſtice aſſigned for the thre ſhires of Caermerthin, Cardigan, and Pembroke. And the fourth of the ſayde Prenotaries ſhall attende vpon the Iuſtice, aſſigned for the thre ſhires of Glamorgan, Breknok, and Radnor. And theſe foure Prenotaries, as often as their ſaide offices ſhall be voyde, ſhall be named and appoynted by the kinges highnes, by his maieſties letters patentes, vnder his great ſeale of Englande. And where one Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Arnolde gentilman hath thoffice of Prenotarie, and clerkeſhippe of the Crowne, by the kinges highneſſe letters patentes, within the ſaid thre ſhires of Northwales: And that one Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Brekenhed, hath thoffice of the Prenotarie and clerkeſhippe of the Crowne by the kinges letters patentes, within the ſaide ſhire of Flynt: And that likewyſe one Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lennerde hath thoffice of the prenotary and clerkeſhippe of the crowne, by the kinges letters patentes, within all the reſidue of the ſaide dominion of Wales: The kinges maieſtie is pleaſed &amp; contented, that the ſaid thre Prenotaries ſhal haue, vſe, &amp; enioy, their ſaid offices accordinge to the effecte of the ſaid letters patentes to them therof made, doinge their duties and attendaunce by them ſelues, or their ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent deputies, at euery of the ſaide ſeſſions, to be kepte within the ſhires, wherunto they be ſo appoynted.</p>
            <p>¶ Item there ſhalbe a Marſhall and a Crier in euery of the circuites and lymyttis, allotted to the ſaid Iuſtices, whiche ſhalbe named by the ſayde Iuſtices, within the lymyttis of their auctoritie and commyſſiumlon, in lyke maner and fourme as Iuſtices of aſſyſe do in Englande. And the ſaide officers ſhall attende vpon the ſaide Iuſtices in their circuites, in their owne propre perſons, and not by their deputies.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25950:5"/>
            <p>And that the Marſhall ſhall haue vpon euery iudgement, and euery fyne four pens: and the crier a peny. And vpon the acquitalles of felons, and of them, that ſhalbe deliuered by proclamation, or deliuered out of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon maynpriſe, before any of the ſaid Iuſtices, the Marſhall ſhal haue foure pens, and the crier a peny.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that euery of the ſaide prenotaries, within the limittes of their offices, ſhall take ſuch fees, as hereafter ſhall be expreſſed: That is to ſay, for the writinge of plees, and ingroſſynge of writtes of entre in the poſt, writtes of right, <hi>Quod ei deforceat,</hi> or any other writtes, purſued by thaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the parties, fyue ſhillinges. And if it be with a duple voucher, then ſex ſhyllinges and .viii. <abbr>d.</abbr> &amp; for the exemplification therof, two ſhillinges. And for the engroſſing of fynes, to haue for euery fyne thre ſhillinges, and foure pens: And if it be with proclamations, then four ſhillinges.</p>
            <p>¶ Item for euery bill of debte detinue treſpas and all other actions per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonalles, ſued before the ſaid Iuſtices in their circuites, vnder the ſumme of .xl. <abbr>s.</abbr> the Prenotaries ſhall haue, for the firſte byll, iiii. <abbr>d.</abbr> for the ſecond byll, foure. <abbr>d.</abbr> and for the third byll foure. <abbr>d.</abbr> And for the entre of euery de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, plee in barre, replication, and reioynder, in and vpon euery ſuch actions, ſo that he do enrolle the ſame in parchement, foure pens. And for euery venite <abbr>fac,</abbr> tales, habeas corpora, et <abbr>diſtr</abbr> in the ſame actions, foure pens: and for the iudgement, four pens. And for euery writte of execution, in euery ſuch action, ſex pens: And for euery warrant of atturney, in euery ſuch action, as well for the playntiffes as for defendantes, foure pens.</p>
            <p>¶ Item in all actions of detinue treſpas and all other actions perſonall, wherin the dutie debte or damage, amounteth to the ſumme of fourtie ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges, or aboue, which ſhalbe ſued by billes before the ſaide Iuſtices, the prenotarie ſhall haue for the firſt bill, foure pens, for the ſeconde bill .iiii. <abbr>d.</abbr> for the thirde byll foure pens. And for euery of the declaration, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, replication, and reioynder, if it be enrolled in parchment, eyght pens: And for the venire <abbr>fac,</abbr> tales habeas corpora, et <abbr>diſtr,</abbr> for euery of them, ſex pens: and for the iudgement eyght pens, and for the warrant of atturney, foure pens: and for euery writte of execution vpon the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in ſuch billes, ſex pens.</p>
            <p>¶ Item in originall writtes, ſued vpon euery action perſonall, returna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before the ſaid Iuſtices, the prenotaries ſhall haue for euery iterum ſum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſex pens, for euery diſtres in treſpas, ſex pens, and for the declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, eyght pens: for the anſwere, replication and reioynder, for euery of them, if they be inrolled and engroſſed, as is afore ſaide, twelue pens. For the venire <abbr>fac,</abbr> tales, habeas corpora, et <abbr>diſtr,</abbr> for euery of them, ſex pens: and the prenotaries to haue for the entre of the iudgementes in euerye ſuch action, twelue pens. And for euery writte of execution, ſued vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſame ſex pens. For the exemplification of euerye recorde, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the ſaide actions, two ſhillinges. For euery warrant of atturney, foure pens. In all actions Reals and mixte, aſſiſes, quare impedit,
<pb facs="tcp:25950:6"/>appeales of felonie, murther, or mayme, the Prenotarie to haue for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration or playnte, two ſhillinges: and for the plee in barre, replication, reioinder, ſurreioinder, for euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they be enrolled, as is aforeſaid, twelue pens: &amp; for the writing of euery venire <abbr>fac,</abbr> Tales, habeas corpora &amp; <abbr>diſtr</abbr> vpon the ſame, for euery of them ſex pens: and for the entre of the iudgement, in euery of the ſaid actions &amp; appeles, two ſhillinges: And for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> writyng of the writtes of execution, made vpon euery of the ſaid actions, appeles, and aſſiſes, twelue pens: And for writtes of graunde Cape and petie cape, and writtes of view, writtes vpon voucher, and al other writtes in euery ſuch action or actions, twelue pens: And for euery warrant of atturney, for the defendantes or for the demaundantes, or playntiffes, in euery ſuch action real, aſſiſe appele, &amp; quare impedit, four pens: And for the eſſoynes in euery ſuch action, foure pens: and for the adiournament, two pens: &amp; for the bayle of euery perſon of felonye, twelue pens: and for the bayle for treſpas, ſex pens: And for the apparaunce and baylynge of common maynpriſe, two pens.</p>
            <p>¶ Item for writing of writtes for the peax, and good aberinge, graunted by any of the ſaid Iuſtices in their ſeſſions, ſex pens: and for the entring of euery Recogniſaunce to be had and taken before the ſaide Iuſtices, for euery cauſe of cauſes, other then before is expreſſed, twelue pens: and if it be with condition, then two ſhillinges. And vpon euery acquitall and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyucraunce of felons or murtherers by verdite or by allowance of perdon, the Prenotaries to haue two ſhillinges. And if it be vpon inditementes, certified from the Iuſtices of the peax, afore the Iuſtices in the great ſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: the clerke of the peax to haue alſo twelue pens. And vpon the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of any ſuſpecte of felonie or murther, by proclamation, the ſaid Preno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie to haue twelue pens.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the kynges maieſtie ſhal haue al fines, iſſues, amercementes and all forfaitures of Recogniſaunces loſt or forfaite before any of the ſaid Iuſtices, in the ſeſſion aforeſaid. And that the ſaid Prenotaries, wi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h in the limittes of their offices, ſhall yerely extrete the ſame into the Eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, appointed for that limit, to thintent that proces from thens may be awarded to the ſhireffes, to leuie the ſame to the kinges vſe, as appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: which ſhireffes ſhal yerely make their accomptes, before the kinges Auditors, therunto to be aſſigned and appoynted.</p>
            <p>¶ Item ouer and beſides the ſaid preſident and counſaile and Iuſtices, there ſhalbe Iuſtices of peax and quorum, and alſo one Cuſtos rotulorum in euery of the ſaid twelue ſhires.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the ſaid Iuſtices of peax, Iuſtices of quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; cuſtos rotuloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſaid ſhires, ſhalbe named and appointed by the Chancelor of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion vnder the kinges great ſeale of Englande, by thabuiſe of the preſident counſayle &amp; Iuſtices aforeſaid, or thre of them, of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the ſaid preſident to be one, from time to time, as the caſe ſhall require.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that there ſhal not excede the nomber of .viii. Iuſtices of the peax
<pb facs="tcp:25950:6"/>in any of the ſaid ſhires, ouer and beſydes the preſident counſalle and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices afore ſaid, and the kynges atturney and Solicitour: which preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayle Iuſtices, and the kynges atturney and Solicitour, ſhalbe put in euery commiſſion of peax, in euery of the ſayd twelue ſhires.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that ſuch perſons, as ſhalbe named to be Iuſtices of peax, within euery of the ſayd ſhires, ſhalbe of good name, and fame: and after they be aſſigned by commyſſion, maye vſe and exerciſe thoſtice of the Iuſtice of peax, al be it they may not diſpende twenty pounde, nor be learned in the lawes of the land, without any loſſe damage or penalties, for inſufficiencie of their landes. And that euery of the ſayde Iuſtices of peax, before they ſhall execute their commiſſion, ſhall take their othes before the Chancelor of England, or els before the ſayde preſydent, or one of the ſaide Iuſtices in Wales, by vertue of the kynges writte of <hi>Dedimus poteſtatem,</hi> or before any other perſonne, to be lymited by the lorde Chaunceloure of Englande for that purpoſe: The contentes of which othe, ſhalbe after the forme, as Iuſtices of peax in England vſe to make.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the ſaid Iuſtices of peax, or two of them at the leaſt, wherof one to be of the quorum, ſhall and may kepe their ſeſſions, within the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittes of their commiſſions, foure tymes in the yere, and at other tymes vpon vrgent cauſes, as Iuſtices of peax in Englande vſe to do, and ſhall haue like power &amp; auctoritie in all thinges, &amp; fees of the kynges maieſtie, for the time of their ſitting, aſwell for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, as for their clerkes: &amp; ſhal be bound to vſe and do their offices, in like maner as is vſed in England.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that no Iuſtices of peax, clerke of the peax, nor other clerke of any Iuſtice of peax in Wales, ſhall take for the writyng of any warrant of the peax, or good aberynge, aboue ſex pens, and for entrynge of pleges or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes to pay the kynges fyne vpon any inditement, nyne pens. And if it be with proteſtation, than to take twelue pens: and for a Superſedeas, not aboue eight pens: and for a Recogniſaunce twelue pens. And that all the ſaide Iuſtices of peax ſhall certifie all Recogniſaunces taken before any of them, for the peax, or good aberynge, into their Seſſions, nexte to be holden after the takynge therof. And Recogniſaunce taken before any of them, for ſuſpicious of any maner of felonie, ſhalbe certified before the Iuſtices in the great ſeſſions, next to be holden after the takynge therof, without concelement deteignynge or imbeſelynge of the ſame, vpon ſuche penalties and daungers, as be therfore ordeyned and eſtabliſſhed.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all fines &amp; amerciamentes, before the ſaide Iuſtices of peax loſt and herafter to be loſt, ſhalbe taxed and afferred by two Iuſtices of the peax at the leaſt, wherof one to be of the quorum. And that all ſuch fynes and amerciamentes ſhalbe ſet truely and duely accordyng to the quantite of the offences, without parcialitie or affection.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the ſayd fynes and amerciamentes, and alſo all iſſues loſte before the ſaid Iuſtices of peax, and all forfaitures of Recognylaunces, and other forfaitures before the ſame Iuſtices, ſhall be yerely extreted by
<pb facs="tcp:25950:7"/>the clerkes of the peax, into the Eſcheker, appointed for that lymit, to thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that proces from thens may be awarded, for the leuyenge of the ſame forfaitures and ſommes of mony to the kynges vſe, to the ſhiref of euery countie, as ſhall apperteigne, Who ſhal make therof their accomptes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuche Auditours, as therunto ſhall be aſſygned, ſo that the kynges maieſtie may therof be truely and duely anſwered and ſatyſfied: whiche Auditours ſhall make due allowance to the ſame ſhireffes, for the fees of the Iuſtices and clerkes of the peax, vppon their ſaid accomptes, as is vſed in the realme of Englande.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that there ſhalbe ſhireffes in euery of the ſaid ſhires yerely apoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by the kynges maieſtie. And that none of the ſayde ſhireffes ſhall haue their office of Shirefwike, any longer tyme, than is vſed by the lawes and ſtatutes of England. And for the yerely nominacion of the ſaide ſhirefes, the ſaid lorde preſident Counſaile and Iuſtices of Wales, or thre of them at the leaſt, wherof the ſayd preſident to be one, ſhall yerely nominate thre ſubſtanciall perſons, in euery of the ſaid twelue ſhires, to be ſhirefes of the ſame, and ſhall certifie their names to the lordes of the kynges moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaile, atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding vpon his graces perſon, <hi>Craſtino animarum,</hi> to thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the kinges maieſtie, being therof aduertiſed, may appoint one of them in euery of the ſayd ſhires, to be ſhirefe for that yere, at his moſt gratious wyll and pleaſure, lyke as his highneſſe doth for his realme of Englande. And therupon the ſaid ſhireffes ſhall haue their patentes, and commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnder the great ſeale of England, as ſhireffes of England haue, and ſhal make and take othes and knowledges of Recogniſaunces, before the preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Iuſtices, or one of them, by vertue of the kynges writte of <hi>Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus poteſtatem,</hi> to be directed for the ſame, for the due execution of their offices, and for their iuſte and true accomptes before the kinges Auditour or Auditors aſſigned for Wales.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that euery of the ſaide ſhireffes ſhall haue full power and aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, within the lymittes of their ſhirefwike, to do and vſe their offices, as ſhireffes in Englande, and ſhall accompliſſhe and execute, without any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour drede or corruption, all maner of wryttes, proces, iudgementes, and executions, and all maner common Iuſtice, apperteinynge to their offices of ſhireffes, and all laufull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes and preceptes, of the ſayde preſident, Counſayle and Iuſtices of Wales, and alſo of the Iuſtices of the peax, Eſchetors, and Crowners, and euery of them, in all thinges ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteyning to theyr offices and auctorities.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the ſayd ſhireffes ſhall do and be bound to do all and euery other thynge and thynges for the miniſtration of Iuſtice, and for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the kinges peax, and the apprehenſion and repreſſe of tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, mutherers, theues, felons, and other offendours, as ſhireffes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland do vſe, and be bound to do within the realme of Englande.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the ſaid ſhireffes ſhal yerely accompt before ſuch the kinges Auditor or Auditours, and ſhalbe aſſigned and appoynted by the kynges
<pb facs="tcp:25950:7"/>maieſtie for his ſaide dominion of Wales. And that euery of the ſaide ſhireffes ſhall haue yerely for his fee, fiue pounde.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all maires, ſhireffes, ſtewardes, bailiffes, &amp; other miniſters and officers of iuſtice, of euery countie, lordſhip towne and place, within the ſaid dominion of Wales, and all and ſingular the kinges ſubiectes of the ſame, ſhalbe alwayes obedient attendant and aſſiſting to the ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, counſaile and Iuſtices of Wales, and euery of them, &amp; ſhall obey the kinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes &amp; proces, from them or any of them directed, and all the laufull &amp; reaſonable preceptes of the ſaide preſident, counſaile and Iuſtices, and euery of them. And alſo ſhalbe obedient to all the ſaid Iuſtices of peax ſhireffes and Eſchetors, within the limittes of their ſaide auctorities, as well for common adminiſtration and due execution of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as in all other thinges apperteyning to their duties and offices.</p>
            <p>¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Eſchet ors ſhalbe named in euery of the ſaid ſhires, by the lord Treſourer of Englande, by thaduiſe of the ſaid preſident, counſayle, and Iuſtices, or thre of them at the leaſt, wherof the ſaid preſident to be one: which Eſchetors ſhal make &amp; take their othes, &amp; knowledge their recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces before the ſaid preſident, or one of the ſaid Iuſtices, by vertu of the kinges wryt of <hi>Dedimus poteſtatem,</hi> to be directed for the ſame, for the due execution of their offices, and for their true accompt, to be made before the kinges auditor or auditors, to be aſſigned for the ſame: which othe &amp; reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gniſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhalbe agreable to the othe &amp; recogniſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vſed for the Eſchetors in England. And the Eſchetors ſhall yerely haue their patentes &amp; commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, vnder the great ſeale of Englande, &amp; ſhall haue power and auctorite to exerciſe their offices, in like maner and fourme as Eſchetours in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and ſhalbe bounde to all lawes and ſtatutes of Englande.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all ſuch perſons, as ſhal be appointed to the ſaid offices, ſhal and may exerciſe their offices, if they may diſpende yerely .v. <abbr>li.</abbr> of frehold: any ſtatutes of Englande to the contrary therof not withſtandinde. And that euery of the ſaid Eſchetors ſhall make their accomptes yerely before ſuch auditour or auditours, as ſhalbe aſſigned by the kinges maieſtie, to here and determyne his highnes accompte for his reuenues and profittes of the ſaide dominion of wales.</p>
            <p>¶ Item there ſhall be two crowners, to be elected in euery of the ſaid .xii. ſhires as is vſed in England, by vertue of the kinges writte, <hi>De coronato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re eligendo,</hi> to be awarded out of the kinges chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cery of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And that the ſaid crowners ſhal haue like power &amp; auctorite, to do &amp; exerciſe their of fices, &amp; haue like fees, as is limitted by the lawes &amp; ſtatutes of England.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, that the writte, <hi>De coronatore eligendo,</hi> to choſe the Crowners within the ſaid countie of Flint, ſhalbe directed out of the Eſcheker of Cheſter.</p>
            <p>¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the ſaid Iuſtices of the peax, or two of them at the leaſte, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one of them to be of the quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhall appoynte &amp; name in euery hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred, within the limittes of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion, two ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciall gentilmen or yemen,
<pb facs="tcp:25950:8"/>to be the chiefe Conſtables of the hundred, wherin they inhabite: whiche two conſtables of euery hundred, ſhall haue eſpeciall regarde to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the kinges peax: and ſhall and may do and vſe theyr offices in all and ſinguler thinges, as is vſed by the high conſtables of the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredes in Englande: And ſhall be bounde to all thinges, as high conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the hundredes in England be bounde to do.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that euery of the ſaide ſhireffes ſhall haue a gaile for priſoners within ſome conuenient place of the caſtels of the ſhire townes, where he is ſhirefe, or in ſuche other conuenient place, as by the ſayd preſident coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile and Iuſtices, or thre of them, wherof the ſaide preſident to be one, ſhalbe appointed: Any patent or graunt heretofore made to any perſon or perſons, of the conſtableſhip, or kepinge of any of the ſaid caſtelles, in any wiſe not withſtandinge. And that the ſhireffe ſhall make the Bayliffes of the hundredes: and they to attende vpon the Iuſtices in euery of theyr courtes and ſeſſions.</p>
            <p>¶ Prouided alwayes, that the conſtables of the kinges caſtelles within euery of the ſaid ſhire townes of Wales, ſhal not be charged with the gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and of all the priſoners, that ſhall be committed to their warde, lyke as they haue hertofore ben, vnto ſuch time conuenient places for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, be aſſigned to the ſaide ſhireffe.</p>
            <p>¶ Item the ſaid ſhireffes ſhall kepe their counties monethly, and their hundred courtes, for plees vnder fourtie ſhillinges, as is vſed in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and ſhall take for the entringe of plaintes, proces, plees and iudgementes, in the ſaid ſhire courtes and hundredes, ſuch ſmall fees as is vſed to be taken in ſhires and hundredes in Englande, and not aboue.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all maner of trialles before them in their ſaid courtes, or be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore any ſtewardes in court barons, ſhalbe by wager of lawe, or verdict of vi. men, at the pleaſure of the partie plaintife or defendaunt, that pleded the plee. And that euery of the ſaide ſhireffes ſhall kepe and holde their Tournes yerely after Eaſter and Michaelmas, as they haue ben vſed in Englande.</p>
            <p>¶ Item the kinges highneſſe ſhall haue all maner of fines, iſſues, amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciamentes and forfaitures, loſte or forfaited in any of the ſayde counties hundredes, courtes, and tournes, to his owne vſe, and the ſhireffe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt for the ſame accordingly.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the extretes of the ſaide tournes, counties, and hundredes ſhalbe viewed, &amp; the fines iſſues and amerciamentes, afferred by the ſaid Iuſtices of aſſiſes of that circuite, before the leuieng of the ſame amercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes or other forfaitures. And that no ſhireffe, or any of his officers, preſume to gather or leuie any ſuche amerciament, or other forfaiture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaide extrete be ſo afferred, vpon peine to forfaite to the kynges vſe fourtie ſhyllinges. And that the ſhireffe vppon euery iudgemente had before him in his countie or hundrede courte, in any playnte vnder fourtye ſhyllynges, ſhall and may awarde a Capias ad ſatiſfaciendum
<pb facs="tcp:25950:8"/>to arreſt the partye condempned: or elles a Fieri <abbr>fac,</abbr> at the libertie of the partie purſuant.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all bylles ſued before the ſaid Iuſtices, in perſonall actions, wherof the debte, dutie, or damage is vnder fourty ſhyllinges: the ſhirefe ſhall haue for the returne of euery byll, two pens: And euery venire <abbr>fac,</abbr> Tales, habeas corpora, et <abbr>diſtr,</abbr> two pens. And for writtes of execution vpon the iudgement, in any ſuch byll, twelue pens.</p>
            <p>¶ Item in billes ſued before the ſaid Iuſtices, in actions perſonalles, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the ſumme of fourtie ſhillinges, the ſhirefe ſhall haue for the returne of euery ſuche byll foure pens: and for the returne of euery venire <abbr>fac</abbr> habeas corpora <abbr>diſtr</abbr> et Tales, foure pens: and for euery writte of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, two ſhillinges. And in all perſonall actions, ſued by originall writtes returnable before the ſayd Iuſtices, the ſhireffe ſhall haue for euery Iteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <abbr>diſtr</abbr> et alias <abbr>diſtr</abbr> foure pens: and for euery venire <abbr>fac</abbr> habeas cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora <abbr>diſtr</abbr> &amp; Tales, ſex pens. And for euery writte of execution to be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon the iudgement, in ſuch actions, two ſhillinges: for the ſeruing of euery writte of Elegit, ſex ſhillinges &amp; eight pens. And in all reall actions or mixt, purſued before the ſayde Iuſtices by origynall wrytte, for returne of euery originall, two willinges. And for the returne of euery other writte and iudiciall proces, dependynge vpon the ſame, before iudgemente, two ſhyllinges: And for euery writte of execution, after iudgement, vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry originall, in actions reall or mixt, two ſhyllinges. And for ſeruinge of euery writte of habery <abbr>fac</abbr> ſeiſinam, ſex ſhillynges eyght pens.</p>
            <p>¶ Item for attachementes vpon Capias, or other proces ſued before the ſayd Iuſtices, by originall or iudiciall wrytte, if he returne Cepi corpus, two ſhillinges: and for a Reddit ſe, vpon an exigent of felonye, in appele of murther or mayme, or vpon any indictament of felonie or murther, two ſhillinges. And vpon a Reddit ſe, vpon an exigent of debte, treſpaſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and all other actions perſonalles, twelue pens: And for the making of Repleg. twelue pens, &amp; withernam vpon the ſame, twelue pens. For the turne of euery wrytte of appele or murther, felonie or maime, twelue pens. And vpon all ohter proces growen vpon the ſame, as venire <abbr>fac,</abbr> Tales habeas corpora, et <abbr>diſtr,</abbr> twelue pens. And in euery action taken before the ſhireffes by Iuſtices, for the ſumme therof foure pens: and for euery other proces therupon foure pens. And for euery priſoner deliuered by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitali, or by proclamation, for any maner of felonie twelue pens.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that euery ſhireffe, within the limittes of his auctoritie, maye and ſhall put ſuche perſonnes vnder common maynpryſe, as they haue reaſonable cauſe of ſuſpecte, accordynge to the ſaid acte made for Wales, byndynge ſuch as they ſhall ſo put to common maynpryſe, with two ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſuretyes with them, by Recognyſaunce, to appere before the ſayde Iuſtices, within the limittes of their auctoryties, at the nexte greate ſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to be holden, nexte after the takynge of ſuche bandes: and ſhall certyfye the names of them, that be bounde, before the ſayde Iuſtices at
<pb facs="tcp:25950:9"/>the ſaid ſeſſions accordingly, without concelement therof, at their pleaſure.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that euery perſon, that the ſhireffe taketh to common mainpryſe, to appere before the ſaid Iuſtices, as is afore ſaid, ſhall pay for his main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe two pens, and not aboue. And the ſaid ſhirefe to put no man to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon mainpriſe, but ſuch as he ſuſpecte, and as ſhalbe returned by them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Iuſtices at their ſeſſions, as is afore ſaid. And alſo the ſayde ſhireffe ſhall haue, for the returne of a wrytte of falſe iudgement, out of a baſe court, before the ſaid Iuſtices, two ſhillinges. And that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid ſhireffe ſhall take no maner of fee, for the returne of any of the ſaid writtes of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution afore expreſſed, onles he returne the ſame executed.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that in all and euery ſuch wryttes oryginall or indiciall, or other proces plees or writinges, which be not expreſſed in this ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the fees therof, aſwell for the ſeales as wrytinge, ſhalbe rated by the ſaid preſident Counſaile and iuſtices, or thre of them, wherof the ſaid preſident to be one by their diſcretions from tyme to tyme, as the caſe ſhall require: And that they ſhall haue full power and auctoritie from tyme to tyme to aſſeſſe and appoint, what fee the ſaid ſhirefes, eſchetors, and Crowners, and their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, Prenotaries and their Clerkes, &amp; other miniſters of iuſtice in the ſaid ſhires: ſhall haue, take, and receyue of the kynges ſubiectes for any maner writtes, playntes, plees, proces, returnes, or any other matter or thinge, concernynge or belongynge to the execution of their offices &amp; row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes: and to augment or diminiſh any fee or fees aboue declared as ſhalbe thought by their diſcretions, to be conueniente and mete for the common welth of the kinges ſubiectes of thoſe parties of Wales: any thinge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in this acte to the contrary therof not withſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that from henſforth no maner of perſon or perſons, for murther or felony, ſhalbe put to his fyne, but ſuffre accordynge to the lawes of the realme of Englande, Excepte it pleaſe the kynges maieſtie to pardon him or them. And if the ſayd Iuſtices ſe cauſe of pitie or other conſideration, they may reprie the priſoner, till they haue aduertiſed the kinges maieſtie of the matter.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the acte made in the parliament, holden in the .xxvi. yere of the moſt royall reygne of the kynges maieſtie, concernynge amonge other thinges inquiſitions and trialles of contrefeting, waſſhyng, clipping, and miniſſhinge of the kynges Coyne, murthers, felons, and acceſſaries to the ſame, perpetrated or done within Wales, to be had, made, and determined in the next ſhire, or countie within England adioyning, where the kynges wrytte runneth, and euery article therin conteyned, ſhall ſtand in his full ſtrength and force, accordynge to the tenoure and effecte of the ſame: Any thinge in this ſaid ordinaunce, or any other acte, cauſe, or matter hertofore had or made, to the contrarye therof not withſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶ And all be it the ſame acte as yet was neuer put in execution, for any of the ſayde offences hertofore done or committed within any of the ſayde thre Shyres of North Wales: That is to ſaye, the countyes
<pb facs="tcp:25950:9"/>of Angleſey, Caernaruan, and Merionneth, Be it now declared &amp; enacted by thauctoritie afore ſaid, that the ſaide act, and euery article therin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned, ſhall from henſforth take effect, and be executed in all pointes, for and concerning any of the ſaid offences perpetrated and done, or that here after ſhalbe perpetrated or done, within the ſaid cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of Merionneth, to be enquired of, herd, and determined, within the countie of Salop<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manner and forme, as commonly is and hath ben vſed for any of the ſame or like offences, committed or done within any other countie or place of Southwales: any matter or cauſe here tofore riſen or growen to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary therof notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the towne or hamlet of Abertannad, and all the ground and ſoile within the ſame, which afore this time hath ben taken, reputed, and vſed as percell of the ſaid countie of Merionneth, ſhall from the feaſte of Eaſter next comming, by vertue of this acte, be vnited, annexed &amp; made percell of the ſaid countie of Salop<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and ſo from thenſforth to be reputed taken and vſed for euer, and not to be of any other ſhire or countie of Wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les. And that the ſame towne or hamlet, and all the grounde and ſoile with in the ſame towne or hamlet, be from and after the ſaid feaſt accepted and taken as parte and percell of the hundred of Oſweſtre: and that the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitauntes therof, from the ſaid feaſt, ſhalbe attendant and do euery thing and thinges, with the inhabitauntes of the ſaid hundred of Oſweſter, as the ſame inhabitauntes do or ben bounde to do, any lawes or cuſtomes to the contrarie therof notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>¶ Item in caſe any forein plee or voucher, be herafter pleded or made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any of the ſaid Iuſtices of wales, betwene partie &amp; partie, triable in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſhire within Wales, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where the ſame plee is pleded or voucher made: That tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaid Iuſtices, afore whom the ſame plee or voucher is or ſhalbe pleded or made, ſhall &amp; may ſende the kinges writte, with a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripte of the recorde, mentioning the ſame foren matter of plee or voucher vnder the ſeale to him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, vnto the Iuſtice of the countie, where the ſame matter is or ſhalbe triable, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the ſaid Iuſtices, by vertu of the ſaid writ, to ꝑcede to the triall therof, according to the kinges lawes &amp; ſtatutes, which trial ſo before him had, he ſhall remaunde with the hole re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde vnto the Iuſtice, before who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayde plee or voucher was pleded or made: who ther vpon ſhal procede to iudgement, as the caſe ſhall require. ¶ Item in caſe the ſame foren plee voucher or other matter ſo pleded, be triable within the realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: that tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in euery ſuch caſe the iuſtice afore who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame ple or voucher is or ſhalbe pleded had or made, ſhall &amp; may procede to the trial therof, as ſhall apperteigne, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the ſame ſhire of Wales, where the ſame plee voucher or matter was pleded, the ſaid foren plee voucher, or any other thing or mater to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary therof not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding. ¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that no maner of perſon or perſons fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henſforth, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out lauful auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie, ſhall make any rumours, tumultes, vnlauful aſſembles, or outcries at any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid courtes or ſeſſions, nor any outcries or vnlauful aſſembles
<pb facs="tcp:25950:10"/>in great nombres, at any other time or times, except it be for the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or purſuynge of murtherers or felons, vpon paine of impryſonment and greuous fyne to be taxed and ſet vpon them by the ſaid preſident and counſaile, or by the Iuſtices or other officer, before whom ſuch miſbeha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui our ſhall happen to be committed.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all manors landes tenementes meſwages &amp; other heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, &amp; all rightes &amp; tytles to the ſame, in any of the ſaid ſhires of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, deſcended to any maner perſon or perſons, ſyth the feaſt of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite of ſaint Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baptiſt, in the .xxxiii. yere of our ſaide ſouerayne lordes reigne, or that herafter ſhall deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, be taken, enioied, vſed &amp; holden as En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſſh tenure to all intentes, according to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lawes of this realme of Englande, &amp; not to be partable among heyres males, after the cuſtome of Gauelkind, as hertofore in diuerſe partes of Wales hath ben vſed and accuſtomed. And that the ſame lawe, from and after the ſaid feaſt of ſaint John<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baptiſt, in the ſaide .xxxiii. yere, be vſed, taken and exerciſed in the ſaide countie of Mommoth, &amp; in all ſuch lordiſhyppes and other places, as by vertue of the ſaide acte, made in the ſaid .xxvii. yere, or by any other acte or actes, made or to be made, were and ſhall be annexed, vnyted, or knyt to any of the ſhires of Salop<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Herford, <abbr>Glouc,</abbr> or other ſhires: any lawes vſages or cuſtomes, hertofore had or vſed to the contrary therof not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that no mortgages of landes, tenementes, or heredytamentes, made or had after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid feaſte of ſaint Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baptiſt, which was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid xxxiii. yere of the raygne of our ſaide ſouerayne lord, or that herafter ſhall be had or made, within any of the ſaide ſhires or places, ſhalbe herafter alowed or admitted, otherwyſe then after the courſe of the common lawes and ſtatutes of the realme of Englande: any vſage or cuſtome hertofore had to the contrarye therof not withſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶ Item it ſhalbe lefull to all perſons, to alien, ſell or otherwyſe put away their landes tenementes, &amp; heredytamentes within the ſaid countrey or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of Wales, the countie of Mommoth, &amp; other places annexed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the ſhires in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, from them &amp; their heires, to any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in fee ſymple or fee tayle, for terme of lyfe or for terme of yeres, after the maner, &amp; accordyng as is vſed by the lawes, of the realme of England: Any welſhe lawe or cuſtome, hertofore vſed in the ſaide countrey or domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of wales, to the contrary herof not withſtandinge. This artycle to take effect from &amp; after the ſaid feaſt of the Natiuite of ſaint Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, whiche was in the ſaid .xxxiii. yereof our ſaid ſouerayne lordes reigne. ¶ Item if any perſon or perſons, hauynge landes or tenementes within the ſaide dominion of Wales, bene or here after ſhalbe bounde within the realme of Englande by obligation, vpon the ſtatute of the ſtaple, or by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognyſaunce, and paye not the dette, as ſhall apperteyne: that then vpon cognyſaunce, and paye not the dette, as ſhall apperteyne: that then vpon certyficate therof made into the kinges Chauncery of Englande, by the Clerke of the ſtaple, or by any Iuſtice of recorde, before whom ſuch reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnyſaunce
<pb facs="tcp:25950:10"/>ſhalbe knowledged, proces ſhalbe made to the ſhireffes of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, out of the Chauncery of Englande, after the forme as is vſed to be made vppon ſtatutes and recognyſaunces, by the courſe of the lawes of England, for due leuyenge and payinge of the ſayd dette.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it enacted by auctoritie aforeſaid, that for ſuch recogniſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces as be or herafter ſhalbe taken and knowledged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the kynges Iuſtices of his highnes benche or common place in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, proces ſhalbe had and purſued immediatly, out from the ſayd Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, as is vſed vpon recogniſaunces, taken before the ſayd Iuſtices, by the common courſe of the lawes of Englande.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all ſuch wryttes, billes, playntes, plees, proces, chalenges, and trialles, ſhalbe vſed throughout all the ſhires afore ſaide, before the ſayd Iuſtices in their ſeſſions, as is vſed in Northwales, or as ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſed by the ſaid preſydent, counſayle and Iuſtices, or thre of them, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſayde preſydent to be one, for the good miniſtration of Iuſtice to be had in euery of the ſayd ſhyres.</p>
            <p>¶ Item where the lord ſhyp of Hope, with diuers other lordſhyps, pariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, townes and hamlettes, were by an acte of Parliament, made in the xxxiii. yere of the reygne of our ſayd ſouerayne lorde, appoynted and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated from the ſayd countye of Denbigh, to the countye of Flynt, and by the ſame acte were made parte, parcell and members of the ſame countye of Flynt: afore which appoyntment or tranſlation, diuers indictamentes and preſentementes, as well felonye as other offences, were had and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the kynges hyghnes, before the Iuſtice of the ſaid countie of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigh, in the great ſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s there, &amp; ſome before the Iuſtices of the peax, with in the ſame countye, for offences ſuppoſed to be done within diuerſe of the ſayde lordſhyppes ſo tranſlated, and alſo diuers iudgementes gyuen ar ſuite of parties before the ſaid Iuſtices: and ſome before the ſhirefe of the ſayde countye of Denbigh, for matters ryſen and growen within the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincte of the ſayde lordſhips, or other places, before the tranſlation of the ſame. It is now ordeyned and enacted, that all the ſayde indictamentes and preſentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ſhalbe hard, tried and determmed within the ſaid coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Denbigh, by perſons, as well of the ſayde lordſhip or place, where the ſayde offences were done, or committed, as of other place or places within the ſayd countie of Denbigh, in maner &amp; forme as though the ſayd tranſlation had neuer ben had ne made. And alſo that the ſayd iudgemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes as before gyuen or had betwene partye and partie, before any Iuſtice of recorde, or other officer, within the ſayde countie of Denbigh, for any matter or cauſe, apperynge by the recorde of the ſame, to be growen and ryſen within any of the ſayd lordſhips, pariſhes, townes or hamlettes, ſo tranſlated, ſhall and may be executed by the ſhireffe of the ſayd countie of Denbigh within any of the ſame lordſhyps, or other place ſo tranſlated, the ſayde tranſlation, or any other cauſe or matter to the contrarye therof notwithſtandynge.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25950:11"/>
            <p>¶ Item lyke lawe and ordre to be kept and miniſtred vpon all other lyke tranſlations of any other lordſhippes maners to wnes pariſſhes and other places within Wales, had made or done in this preſent parliament, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other afore or after the ſame tranſlations, or any other cauſe or matter to the contrary therof not withſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Item where there ſhall be diuers and many ſutes taken before the ſaid Iuſtices in plees perſonall, which (as it is thought) can not be tryed before them, in the tyme of the ſaid great ſeſſions, for breuitie of tyme: Therfore, and for the ſpedye triall of theſe matters, thiſſues taken in the ſaid ſuites, ſhall and may be tried at a petie ſeſſions before the deputie iuſtices there as it is &amp; hath ben vſed in the ſaid thre ſhires of Northwales: Except ſuch of the ſaid ſuites, as by the diſcretions of the ſaid Iuſtices ſhalbe thought neceſſarie to be tryed before them ſelues, within their lymittes. And that there ſhall no ſute be taken before any of the ſayd Iuſtices by byll, vnder the ſumme of twenty ſhyllynges.</p>
            <p>¶ Item if any murther or felonye here after be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted or done within Wales: that then the partie or parties, to whom any ſuch offence ſhal hap to be committed, ſhall in no wiſe take any ende or agrement with the often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in that behalfe, nor with any other in his name or behalfe, onles the ſad partye fyrſt make the ſayd preſident and counſayle, or one of the ſayd Iuſtices, priuey vnto the ſame, vpon payne of impriſonment, and greuous fyne to be ſette and adiuged, at the diſcretion of the ſayd preſident, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle &amp; iuſtices, or two of them, wherof the ſayd preſident to be one: The ſame peyne &amp; penaltie to extende, as well to and agaynſt ſuch, as ſhall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, moue, or procure, any ſuch ende or agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t made although the ſame labour, motion, or procurement neuer take effecte, to make any ende or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grement, as agaynſt him or them, with whom ſuch ende or agrement ſhall be made, if the ſame happen to take effecte.</p>
            <p>¶ Item where diuers lordſhyppes marchers, as well in Wales as in the borders of the ſame, now beynge by acte of parliament annexed to diuers ſhires of England, be lately comen to the kynges handes, by ſuppreſſion of houſes, by purchaſe or atteyndors: and now be vnder the ſurueyour of the court of augmentations, or of the kinges generall Surueyours, the liberties, frauncheſes and cuſtomes of all which lordſhips, be lately reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by act of parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t made in the .xxxii. yere of his moſt gratious reigne: Neuertheles his maieſtie willeth and commaundeth, that no other liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, frauncheſes or cuſtomes, ſhall from henſforth be vſed, claymed or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſed within the ſayd lordſhyps nor any other lordſhyps within Wales or the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of Mommoth, who ſo euer be lorde or owner of the ſame: but only ſuch libertyes, frauncheſes &amp; cuſtomes, as be gyuen &amp; commaunder-to the lordes of the ſame lordſhyps, by force &amp; vertue of the ſaid act of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, made for Wales: in the ſayd .xxvii. yere of his graces reigne, and not altered ne taken awaye by his ordinaunce: the ſayde acte made in the ſayd .xxxii. yere, or any other acte graunt lawe or cuſtome to the contractye
<pb facs="tcp:25950:11"/>therof not withſtandinge</p>
            <p>¶ Item that if any perſon or perſons, theyr aunceſters, or they whoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate the ſame perſon, or perſons haue, or hath in peaſeable poſſeſſion of any landes or tenementes in Wales, by the ſpace of fyue yeres, withoute let interrupcion or lefull claime: That then the ſame perſon or perſons ſhal ſtill continue their poſſeſſion, vntyll ſuche tyme as it be lawfully recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red agaynſt them, by the order of the kynges lawes, or by Decree of the preſident and counſayle there.</p>
            <p>¶ Item in actions perſonalles, taken and purſued before the ſaid Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Wales by oryginall writte, or bill, if nine of the Iurie be ſworne, to trye the iſſue betwene the partie playntyfe and the defendant, &amp; the reſidue of the ſaid Iury make defaute, or be tried out: them the ſhireffes ſhall and may immediatly returne other names in the ſaid Iury, de circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus vnto ſuch tyme there be twelue men ſworne, to trye thiſſue betwene them, as before the Iuſtice of Northwales hath ben afore vſed and accuſtomed in ſuch caſes.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that if any goodes or cattelles be ſtolen by any perſon or perſons and ſold in any faire or market, within the ſayd dominion of Wales, that no ſuch ſale ſhall change the propertie therof from the owner of the ſame: but that he may lefully ceaſe take and haue the ſame agayne, vpon profe therof made, the ſayd ſale notwithſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that no perſon or perſons bargayne or bye any maner of beaſt, or other quicke cattell, in any place within Wales, out of the market or faire onleſſe he can bringe forth ſuffycient and credible witnes, of the name of the perſon, what place, and tyme he bought the ſame: vppon payne and daunger of ſuch puniſſhement and fyne, as ſhalbe ſet vppon him, by the ſayd preſydent and counſayle, or any of the ſayd Iuſtices in his circuite, for the ſayd offence, and as he wyll therfore anſwere at his farther peryll.</p>
            <p>¶ Item if any goodes or cattelles be ſtolen within the lymittes, of any of the ſayd ſhires in Wales: that then vpon ſuite therof had and made, the tracte ſhalbe folowed from towneſhip to towneſhip, or lordſhip to lordſhip according to the lawes &amp; cuſtomes in that behalf hertofore vſed in Wales vpon ſuch penaltie and daunger, as heretofore hath ben accuſtomed.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that euery perſon that hath any landes or tenementes in fee ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or fee tayle, or for terme of lyfe, or for terme of any other mannes lyfe being freholde, ſhall and may paſſe in all maner Iuries and trials, as wel in caſe of felonye or murther, as in all actions reall, perſonall and mixte, what ſoeuer they be, atteint only except: And alſo may be impanelled, and inquire of all concelementes, forceble entres, and other cauſes of inquirie for the kynges maieſtie, all be it he may not diſpende fourtye ſhillinges by yere. Sauinge to euery man his lawfull chalenge for any other cauſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the lawes of this realme of Englande.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that no iurrour ſhall paſſe in Atteint, onles he may diſpend four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye ſhillinges by the yere of eſtate of freholde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25950:12"/>
            <p>¶ Item the tenantes and reſiauntes in Wales, ſhall pay theyr tallage at the chaunge of their lordes, in ſuch places, and after ſuche forme, as hath ben hertofore accuſtomed in Wales.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all the kinges ſubiectes and reſiauntes in Wales, ſhal find at all parliamentes herafter to be holden in Englande, knyghtes for the ſhires, and citezyns &amp; burgeſſes for cyties and townes, to be named &amp; cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by auctoryte of the kynges wryt, vnder the great ſeale of England, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the acte in that caſe prouided: and ſhalbe charged and chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all ſubſides &amp; other charges, to be graunted, by the commons of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the ſayd parliamentes, &amp; pay all other their rentes, fermes cuſtomes and duties to the kynges hyghnes, as they haue ben accuſtomed here to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, fines for rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptions of ſeſſions only excepted. which the kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtie of his moſt gratious goodnes and liberalitie, is contented and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to remitte, at the humble ſuite of his ſaid louinge ſubiectes of his ſaid dominion of Wales.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the towne of Hauerford weſt, ſhal after the ende of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament for euer, fynde one burges, for the ſayde towne, at euery parliament after that time to be holden: And the charges of the ſame bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be alwayes borne, by the mayre, burgeſſes &amp; inhabitauntes of the ſaid towne and none other.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the kynges maieſtie ſhall haue all felons goodes, &amp; goodes of perſons outlawed, waif, ſtraies, &amp; all other forfaitures &amp; eſchetes what ſoeuer they be, anſwered thereof by the handes of the ſhireffes: ſauing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the ryghtes and intereſtes of euery of his ſubiectes hauyng laufull tytle to haue the ſame.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that all errours &amp; iudgementes, before any of the of the ſayd Iuſtices at any tyme of the great ſeſſions, in plees realles or mixt, ſhalbe redreſſed by wrytte of Errour, to be ſued out of the kynges Chauncerye of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, returnable before the kynges Iuſtice of his benche in Englande. as other writtes of errour be in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And that all errours in plees per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall, ſhalbe reformed by bylles, to be ſued before the ſayde preſident and counſayle of Wales, from tyme to tyme, as the partie greued wyll ſue for the ſame. And if in caſe the iudgement be affirmed good, in any of the ſaid writtes of errour or billes, then there to make execution and all other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces therupon, as is vſed in the kynges benche in Englande. And that the purſuantes in euery ſuch wrytte of errour or byll, do pay lyke fees therfore as is vſed in England.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that no execution of any iudgement gyuen or to be gyuen in any baſe court, be ſtayed or deferred by reaſon of any writte of falſe iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but that execution ſhall and may be had and made at all tymes, before the reuerſall of the ſaid iudgement, the purſuyte of the ſaid wryt notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng. And in caſe the ſaid iudgement happen after to be reuerſed: then the partie purſuant to be reſtored to all that he hath loſt by the ſaid iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, accordynge to the lawes of the realme.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25950:12"/>
            <p>¶ Item that all proces for vrgent and weyghty cauſes, ſhall be made and directed into Wales, by the ſpeciall commaundement of the Chauncel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Englande, for the tyme beyng, or any of the kinges counſaile in Englande, as hertofore hath ben vſed: Any thing in this acte to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary therof not withſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the towne of Bewdley, which is within the pariſh of Ribbiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, in the countie of Wigorn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and all the grounde and ſoile of the ſame towne, ſhall from henſforth be vnited, annexed, and made percell of the countie of Wigorn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to be within the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred of Dodingtre. And that all the inhabitauntes of the ſaide towne and pariſſh, ſhall from henſforth be attendaunt, and do euery thinge and thinges, with the inhabitauntes of the ſaide hundred, as the ſame inhabitauntes be now bounde to dó, by the lawes of this realme of Englande. Sauinge alwayes to the burges &amp; inhabitauntes of the ſaid towne of Bewdley, all ſuche liberties and fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſes, as they lawfully had and exercyſed within the ſame towne, before the makyng of this acte, in lyke maner and fourme, as thoughe this acte had neuer ben had or made.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the lordſhip of <abbr>llanſtiffan,</abbr> Vſterloys, and Langham, and the membres of the ſame, and all manors, landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes in the ſame lordſhippe, and the membres of the ſame, be frome henſforth vnited annexed ioyned named accepted and taken as part and parcell of the countie of Carmarthin, and reputed ioyned vnited na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med accepted and taken as parte and percell of the hundred of Derles in the ſaide countie of Carmarthin. And that the tenantes &amp; inhabitauntes of the ſaide lordſhip and membres, be attendant, and do euery thinge and thinges, with the tenantes &amp; inhabitantes of the ſaide hundred of Derles, as the ſaide inhabitauntes now be bounde to do accordynge to the lawes there vſed.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the countie or ſhire courte of the countie of Radnor, ſhall from henſforth be holden, one tyme at new Radnor, and one other tyme at Preſten alternis vicibus, and neuer from henſforth to be kepte or holden at Rather Gowy: Any former acte or other thinge to the contrary therof not withſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶ Item it is further enacted, by the auctoritie aforeſaide, that the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges mooſt royall maieſtie, ſhall and maye at all times here after, from tyme to tyme chaunge, adde, alter, ordre, miniſſhe and refourme, all maner of thinges afore reherſed, as to his mooſt excellent wiſedome and diſcretion ſhall be thoughte conuenient: And alſo to make lawes and ordinaunces for the common welth and good quiet of his ſayde do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynyon of Wales, and his ſubiectes of the ſame, from tyme to tyme, at his maieſties pleaſure: Any thinge conteigned in this acte, or in the ſaide acte made for the ſhite ground of Wales, or any other acte or actes, thinge or thinges, to the contrary therof hertofore made in any wyſe not withſtandinge.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25950:13"/>
            <p>And all ſuche alterations of the premiſſes, or any parte therof. And that all ſuch lawes and ordinaunces, to be herafter made, deuiſed &amp; publiſſhed by auctoritie of this acte, by the kinges maieſtie, in wrytinge vnder his highnes great ſeale, ſhalbe of as good ſtrength vertue &amp; effecte, as if they had ben had and made by auctoritie of parliament.</p>
            <p>¶ Item be it further enacted and ordeined, by auctoritie afore ſaide, that where the kinges maieſtie that now is, by his letters patentes, bearinge date the .i. day of Maye, in the .xxxiiii. yere of his moſt proſperous reigne, demiſed and graunted to William webbe, the ſubſidie and vſage of all wollen clothes, made or to be made in the countie of Mommoth, &amp; in the xij. ſhires in Wales, that is to ſaye, in the countie of Breknok, Radnor, Mountgomery, Caermerthin, Glamorgan, Pembroke, Cardigan, Angle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey Flint, Denbigh, Caernatuan, and Merionneth, and in all and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar townes and other places, whatſoeuer they be, within the precincte and limittes of the ſaid counties, and els where within the dominion of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: To haue and to holde to the ſayd William webbe, &amp; his aſſignes for certayne yeres yet enduringe, that the ſaide William webbe, his deputies and aſſignes, ſhall haue from henſforth full power and auctoritie by force of this acte, to take for the ſealinge of euery wollen cloth, herafter to be made in the ſaid .xiii. ſhires, &amp; els where, within the ſaid dominion of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, as herafter is declared, &amp; none otherwiſe, that is to ſay, for euery hole pece of friſe .i. <abbr>d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</abbr> euery halfe pece friſe. <abbr>ob.</abbr> euery pece cotton and lininge, beyng .xxiiii. yardes &amp; vnder, a halfpeny. And for euery pece of the ſame, beynge aboue .xxiiii. yardes, one peny: of euery brode clothe, one peny: Of euery pece of karſey, beyng .xviii. yardes and aboue, one peny: Of euery pece of karſey, beyng vnder .xviii. yardes, a halfe peny.</p>
            <p>¶ Prouided alwayes, that this acte, ne nothing therin conteyned, extend not to charge any maner of perſon or perſons, being or that herafter ſhall be inhabitaunt, in any of the ſaid .xiii. ſhires, or els where within the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of Wales, for any clothes, friſes, karſeis, or lininges, made or her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to be made and occupied within their houſes, and not put to ſale to any perſon or perſons, but to their ſeruauntes for their wearinge.</p>
            <p>¶ And further be it enacted by auctoritie afore ſaide, that the ſaide Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nager in Wales, by him ſelfe, or by his ſufficient deputie or deputies ſhall in all thinges to his office apperteyninge, do and be bounde to do, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere in euery caſe, like and according as all and euery other Aulnager in the realme of England do, or ought to do, according to the lawes &amp; ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the realme of England. And for the contrary doinge or exerciſinge of the ſaid office, ſhall in euery caſe and degre ſuffre, as by the ſaide lawes and ſtatutes is ordeyned, eſtabliſſhed or enacted for Aulnagers vnder the lord Treaſourer of Englande for the time beynge.</p>
            <p>¶ And furthermore the kynges maieſtie is contented &amp; pleaſed, not with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandinge the ſtatute made in the .xxvii. yere of his moſt gratious reigne: that where there ſhulde be but .xii. ſhires in Wales, that the towne of Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerford
<pb facs="tcp:25950:13"/>weſt, ſhalbe a countie in it ſelfe, as it hath ben before this tyme v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, at the wyll and pleaſure of the kinges ſaid maieſtie: and that it ſhalbe ſeparated from the countie of Pembroke, at the kynges ſayde pleaſure. And that the kynges high Iuſtice of the ſayd countie of Pembroke, ſhall be hygh Iuſtice of the ſaid countie and towne of Hauerford weſt, and ſhal haue like power and auctorite, to and for the miniſtration of Iuſtice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayd countie and towne of Hauerforde weſt, as is lymitted and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to the ſayd Iuſtice to and for the adminiſtration of Iuſtice in the ſayde countie of Pembroke. And that the Mayre, ſhireffe, bayliffes, and burgeſſes of the ſayd countie and towne of Hauerford weſt, from tyme to tyme, ſhalbe as well attendaunt, &amp; obeye all preceptes &amp; commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the preſident &amp; counſayle of our ſayde ſoueraigne lorde the kinge in his marches of Wales, as alſo ſhalbe attendaunt to all preceptes &amp; proces awarded or directed, by the ſayd hygh Iuſtice, vnto the ſhireffe of the ſaid countie and towne of Hauerforde weſt: and to make returne therof. And the ſayd ſhireffe of the ſayde countie and towne, ſhall ſerue all preceptes and proces, directed from the ſayd high Iuſtice, in like maner &amp; forme, as the ſhireffe of the ſaid countie of Pembroke is bound to do, and according to the effecte and purport of the kynges ordinaunces, in that behalfe had made and prouided. And that it ſhalbe lefull vnto the ſayd maire, ſhireffe, Bayliffes, and burgeſſes of the ſayd countie and towne of Hauerford weſt afore ſayd, to vſe and exerciſe all lefull liberties and grauntes, by the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges maieſtie, or his noble progenitours, to them graunted and confirmed, at the kynges maieſties wyll and pleaſure, accordinge to the lawes of the realme of England, &amp; not other wiſe. And that the iudicial ſeale of the ſaid ſhires of Pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>broke, Carmerthin, &amp; Cardigan, be in the cuſtodie &amp; keping of the kynges hygh Iuſtice there for the tyme beynge, ſhalbe vſed in the ſaid countie and towne of Hauerford weſt, as the originall and iudiciall ſeale the ſame towne and countie. And that the ſaid Iuſtice of the ſaid ſhires, of Pembroke, Carmeden, and Cardigan, ſhall haue like power and auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, by vertue of the kynges letters to him made, as well to do all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thyng and thinges, concernynge common iuſtice to be miniſtred within the ſaid towne &amp; countie of Hauerford weſt, as he hath in his ſaide letters patentes, within any of the ſayde ſhyres, of Pembroke, Carmerden, and Cardigan.</p>
            <p>¶ Prouided alwaye, that this article, touching and concerning the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and towne of Hauerford weſt, and all thinges therin conteyned, ſhall ſtande and endure, but onely at the kynges maieſties wyll and pleaſure, and none otherwyſe.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alway that this acte, or any thing therin conteyned, ſhal not be preiudicial nor hurtful to any perſon or perſons, or bodies po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litike, for or concerning any la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, tenementes, rentes, ſeruices, bondmen, tolles or other hereditame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, but that they &amp; euery of them, their heyres, ſucceſſours and aſſignes, &amp; the heyres, ſucceſſours and aſſignes of euery
<pb facs="tcp:25950:14"/>of them, ſhall haue, holde, and enioye their landes tenementes, rentes, ſeruyces, boundmen and other their hereditamentes, in ſuch like maner, forme and condition, as they had the ſame before the makynge of this act, and as if this acte had neuer ben had ne made.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alſo that this acte, nor any thyng therin conteyned, ſhalbe hurtfull or preiudiciall to any perſon or perſons, for or concernynge any office or offices, whiche they or any of them haue by vertue of any the kynges letters patentes, beynge now in force before the makynge of this acte, nor to the fees of money, vſed and accuſtomed to be payd for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe of any ſuch offices: but that euery perſon &amp; perſons, hauynge ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyces and fees, and their ſubſtitutes and deputyes, ſhall and maye haue and exerciſe their ſaide offices, as is lymitted by this acte, and as they moughte haue done before the makynge of this acte. And ſhall alſo haue and perceyue all ſuche fees, for the exercyſe of the ſayde offices, in as large and ample maner, forme and condicion, as they myght afore the makynge of this acte, and as if this acte had neuer ben had ne made.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, that all landes, tenementes, and heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, within the ſayde deminion of Wales, ſhall deſcende to the hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, accordynge to the courſe of the common lawes of the realme of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, accordyng to the tenour and effecte of this acte, and not to be vſed as Gauelkynde: any thinge conteyned in theſe prouiſions or any of them to the contrary therof not withſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶ Prouided alwayes, that this acte, ne any clauſe, article, or thyng ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conteyned, be in any wyſe preiudiciall or hurtfull to George Blunte eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyer, ſonne and heyre of ſyr Iohu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Blunte knight deceaſed, for or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the offices of ſtewardſhyps of the kynges lordſhips or manours of Bewdley and Clebury, or any other offyce or offyces hertofore graunted vnto the ſayde George Blunte, by the kynges letters patentes, ſealed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the great ſeale of England, for terme of lyfe of the ſame George or for or concernyng any fees, wages, rewardes, annuites, profittes, commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, aduauntages or emolumentes, apperteyning or belonginge vnto the ſayd offices or any of them: but that the ſayd George, his deputie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, ſhall and may at all tyme and tymes, durynge the lyfe of the ſame George, haue, hold, exercyſe, and enioy the ſame offices and euery of them, and alſo perceyue, leuie, and take the fees, wages, rewardes, and all other profyttes and commodities, to the ſame offices and euery of them, or to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them belongyng: or in any wiſe apperteynyng, in as large and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple maner, forme, and condition, to all intentes, conſtructions and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as though this acte had neuer ben had or made: any thynge before in this acte conteyned to the contrarie not withſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Prouided alwayes that all libertyes, francheſes and priuileges of the duchy of Lancaſtre, or in any wyſe apperteyning to the ſame, ſhalbe of the ſame force plyght qualitie, goodnes and condition, and maye be vſed in as large and ample maner, as they were before the makynge of this acte,
<pb facs="tcp:25950:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>and as if this acte had neuer ben had or made: any thinge in this acte to the contrary therof not withſtanding.</p>
            <trailer>¶ <hi>FINIS.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Barthelet regis impreſſor excudebat, Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</hi> ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> ☜</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
